Guide to the Turner family papers, 1778-1929 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Turner family papers 1778-1929 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Turner family
3.5 Linear Feet Approx. 1316 Items
The Turner family was based in Van Buren, Crawford County, Arkansas.
Correspondence, papers, diaries, and scrapbooks of Jesse Turner, Sr. (1805-1894), lawyer, jurist, and Whig politician of Van Buren, Ark.; his wife, Rebecca (Allen) Turner (1823-1917); their son, Jesse Turner, Jr. (1856-1919); and other members of the Turner and Allen families, relating to law practice, family history and personal matters, political activities in Arkansas and the U.S. (1840-1900), secession in Arkansas, the Arkansas Constitution of 1836, social life and customs in Arkansas, life during Reconstruction, and U.S. presidential elections of 1848 and 1860. Correspondents include prominent Arkansas attorneys Albert Pike and Absalom Fowler. There are also a number of letters between Rebecca Allen and Jesse Turner before their marriage, and letters from Rebecca to her son Jesse Jr., as well as diaries written by his mother (1857-1859) chronicling his early childhood.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
However, collection may contain materials to which the Acknowledgment of Legal Responsibilities and Privacy Rights form applies. Patrons must sign this form before using this collection.
Also, all or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. Consequently, there may be a 24-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Turner family papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as gifts and additions from 1938 to 1954.
Biographical Note
Jesse Turner, Sr., was born in Orange County, North Carolina in 1805 to a family of Irish immigrants. He received his legal training in Chapel Hill from William McCauley, then left Carolina in 1830. He settles in Van Buren, Arkansas, in 1838, and was elected to the state legislature in the same year as a Whig party member. He rose to prominence in state and national politics, and in 1861 he served as a delegate to the secession convention. He married Rebecca Allen Turner in 1855; in 1856 they had a son, Jesse, who died at an early age in 1919, a few years after his mother. Jesse Turner, Sr. died in 1894.
Collection Overview
Correspondence and papers of Jesse Turner, Sr., lawyer, jurist, and Whig politician of Van Buren, Arkansas; his wife, Rebecca (Allen) Turner; their son, Jesse Turner, Jr.; and other members of the Turner family, relating to law practice, family affairs, political activities in Arkansas and the U.S. (1840-1900), the Arkansas Constitution of 1836, secession in Arkansas, social life and customs in Arkansas, and life during Reconstruction. Jesse Turner Sr.'s letters on secession are especially invaluable, as are his letters and those from prominent lawyers and jurists commenting on state and national politics. Correspondents include prominent Arkansas lawyers Albert Pike and Absalom Fowler. There are also a number of letters between Rebecca Allen and Jesse Turner before their marriage, and letters from Rebecca to her son Jesse Jr.
The collection also includes legal records; school records, college letters from the University of Virginia, and other papers of Jesse Jr.; a diary belonging to Rebecca Allen Turner (1857-1859) that comments on her young son's activities; a journal of work on steamboats in the West (1840-1850); and scrapbooks relating to the presidential elections of 1848 and 1860.
For a more detailed description of the context and contents of this collection, please consult with a reference archivist for access to the Rubenstein's digitized cardfile.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Fowler, Absalom
Pike, Albert, 1809-1891
Turner, Jesse, 1805-1894
Turner, Jesse, 1856-1919
Turner, Rebecca Allen, 1823-1917
Allen family
Turner family
Lawyers -- Arkansas -- Correspondence
Lawyers -- Southern States
Mothers and sons
Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 1848
Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 1860
Reconstruction (U.S. history, 1865-1877)--Arkansas
Secession -- Arkansas
Steamboats -- West (U.S.)
Arkansas -- History
Arkansas -- Politics and government
United States -- Politics and government -- 19th century
West (U.S.)--Description and travel
Diaries
Scrapbooks
Separated Material
The following three volumes were transferred to the Duke University Law Library: Jesse Turner, Sr., Briefs of Suits In the Supreme Court of Arkansas, 1891-1901, 1901-1908, 1908-1911.
Contents of Collection
- Turner Family papers, 1778-1929 and undated, (7 boxes)
  - Papers, 1778-1855, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Papers, 1856-1874, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Papers, 1875-1895, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Papers, 1896-1914, (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - Papers, 1915-1929 and undated, (3 folders) (Box 5)
  - Pamphlets, and scrapbook from the presidential campaign, 1846-1848 (Box 6)
    Box contains one scrapbook and several dozen pamphlets.
  - Clippings and miscellaneous papers, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Scrapbook of presidential campaign, 1860 (Volume L:5890)
  - Little Jesse's Diary, 1857-1858, Van Buren, Ark., 400 pp. (Volume M:6888)
  - Little Jesse's Diary, 1858-1859, Van Buren, Ark., 224 pp. (Volume M:6889)